A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential records, Video Recordings, Series 20 FA798
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential records, Video Recordings, Series 20
1974-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979)
FA798
5.4 Cubic Feet 10 wide-letter document boxes.
64 video recordings.
Related Materials
Transcripts and sound recordings of the Senate Rules Committee hearings on Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential nomination, as well as other related documents, are located in Nelson A. Rockefeller vice presidential records, New York Office, Series 10 (FA380).
Scope and Contents
Contains 64 videotapes that relate to Nelson A. Rockefeller's term as United States Vice President.
These tapes include: the 1976 Moreland Act Commission hearings on New York State Nursing Home corruption; the 1974 Senate Rules Committee hearings on Rockefeller's Vice Presential nomination; and the confirmation of Nelson A. Rockefeller.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Moving Images
- Video Recordings, 1974-1978; 20; 5.4 Cubic Feet; 64 video recordings.
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Monday - Tape 1, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 1, Tape AV 11980)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy available.
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Monday - Tape 2, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 1, Tape AV 11981)
  - Nursing Home Hearings- Monday - Tape 3, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 1, Tape AV 11982)
  - Nursing Home Hearings- Monday - Tape 4, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 1, Tape AV 11983)
  - Nursing Home Hearings- Monday - Tape 5, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 1, Tape AV 11984)
  - Nursing Home Hearings- Monday - Tape 6, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 1, Tape AV 11985)
  - Nursing Home Hearings- Monday - Tape 7, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 1, Tape AV 11986)
  - Nursing Home Hearings- Monday - Tape 8, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 2, Tape AV 11987)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 9, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 2, Tape AV 11988)
  - Nursing Home Hearings- Tape 10, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 2, Tape AV 11989)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 11, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 2, Tape AV 11990)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 12, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 2, Tape AV 11991)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 13, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 2, Tape AV 11992)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 14, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 2, Tape AV 11993)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 15, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 3, Tape AV 11994)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 16, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 3, Tape AV 11995)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 17, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 3, Tape AV 11996)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 18, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 3, Tape AV 11997)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 19, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 3, Tape AV 11998)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 20, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 3, Tape AV 11999)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Tape 21, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 3, Tape AV 12000)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Moreland Act Commission - Tape 22, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 4, Tape AV 12001)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Moreland Act Commission - Tape 23, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 4, Tape AV 12002)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Moreland Act Commission - Tape 24, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 4, Tape AV 12003)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Moreland Act Commission - Tape 25, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 4, Tape AV 12004)
  - Nursing Home Hearings - Moreland Act Commission - Tape 26, 1976; Sound, Color; U-matic (Box 4, Tape AV 12005)
  - Thursday News Coverage of Announcement to Call Nelson A. Rockefeller to Testify and Interview with Morris B. Abram, 1976; Sound, Color, 37 minutes; U-matic (Box 4, Tape AV 12006)
    Scope and Contents
    Various news reports discussing the Moreland Act Commission's request for Vice President Nelson Rockefeller to testify. Includes: "The Nursing Home Scandals: A Conversation with Morris Abram," a 30-minute interview with the Chairman of the Moreland Act Commission, broadcast on Channel 13.
  - Moreland Act Commission: The Final Report - Channel 13, 1976; Sound, Color, 59 minutes; U-matic (Box 4, Tape AV 12007)
    Interviewer Robert Sam Anson interviews Morris B. Abram. They summarize and discuss outcomes from the Moreland Act Commission's 15-month investigation into corruption in the nursing home industry in New York.
  - Compilation of News Broadcasts: Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Hearings and Today Show Interview with Barbara Walters (NBC-TV), 1974 September - 1974 December 24; Sound, Color, 29 minutes; U-matic (Box 5, Tape AV 12008)
    Various televised new broadcasts reporting on Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential nomination hearings. Includes footage of Nelson Rockefeller answering Senate questions related to his divestiture of assets, President Ford's pardoning of Richard Nixon, the Attica prison riots, and the loan of money to NY/NJ Port Authority Chairman William Ronan. Tape concludes at 11:45 with complete NBC-TV Today Show interview between Rockefeller and Barbara Walters.
  - Washington: Senate Hearings on Nelson Rockefeller - Day One, 1974 September 29; U-matic (Box 5, Tape AV 12009)
    Special PBS-TV report hosted by Jim Leher (National Public Affairs Center for Television. Political analysts Richard Reeves of New York Magazine and author Neal Pierce discuss Nelson A. Rockefeller's finacial assets and family's influences. Leher provides a synposis of the topics that were covered during Day One of Senate questioning. Includes footage from hearings.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day One (Tape 4), 1974 September 26; Sound, Color, 63 minutes; U-matic (Box 5, Tape AV 12010)
    Tape begins with Nelson Rockefeller giving a statement (ending only recorded).
    Rockefeller responds to Senator Howard Cannon's questions regarding Ford's pardon of Nixon, and what would his position be toward a pardon should Rockefeller become President. Also, given the economic power of the Rockefeller family, Cannon questions "How can you conduct yourself in office in a manner that would avoid even the appearance of conflict of interest."
    Rockefeller discusses Rockefeller Foundation and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund. Nelson A. Rockefeller's annual income and income tax paid for each year beginning in the 1960s is discussed in detail. Senator Claiborne Pell continues "conflict of interest" questioning and discusses Rockefeller's past quotes about not wanting to be Vice President.
    Tape concludes with Senator Hugh Scott deriding Congress for not acting quicker on Vice Presidential confirmation hearings. Happy Rockefeller can be seen in the audience.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day One (Tape 5), 1974 September 26; Sound, Color, 63 minutes; U-matic (Box 5, Tape AV 12011)
    Tape begins with Senator Hugh Scott continuing questioning.
    Rockefeller speaks about the need for a Free Press and his relationship with labor. Senator Robert Byrd asks about his "considerable wealth" and what assurances the American people could have that his Vice Presidency won't enrich the "Rockefeller empire." Rockefeller speaks about his investments and those of his brothers.
    After breaking for recess, Senator Robert Byrd begins questioning by asking him about the pardoning powers of the President and about Rockefeller's wealth. Liberty Lobby allegations and Rockefeller's tax returns are detailed as well as his involvement with Bilderberg.
    Senator James Allen asks if Rockefeller has moved "philosophically to the Right." Rockefeller responds by discussing his actions with regard to Welfare and the drug control laws he enacted.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day One (Tape 6), 1974 September 26; Sound, Color, 63 minutes; U-matic (Box 5, Tape AV 12012)
    Senator Mark Hatfield begins questioning. Rockefeller discusses economic topics: inflation, unemployment, balancing the Federal budget, increasing taxes. Rockefeller next discusses his views on the role of the Central Intelligence Agency.
    Senator Harrison Williams begins questioning. Rockefeller discusses the 1971 lawsuit brought against him by the New York Civil Liberty Union, his thoughts regarding Separation of Powers and Executive Priviledge, and about his actions during the Watergate crisis.
    Senator Howard Cannon asks about the Rockefeller trusts increased capital gains in 1970 and why this resulted in Nelson Rockefeller paying no personal income tax that year. Rockefeller reports how he learned he was Ford's Vice Presidential nominee and Ford's phone call to Nixon telling him of this decision. Rockefeller also explains why he had been requesting a Grumman aircraft defense contract for New York.
    Senator Marlow Cook details the monetary amounts of family Foundations and Rockefeller Center. Nelson Rockefeller states that these should not be grouped into one category because Rockefeller Center is a business.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day Two (Tape 7), 1974; Sound, Color, 63 minutes; U-matic (Box 5, Tape AV 12013)
    Tape begins with special PBS-TV report: "Washington: Senate Hearings on Nelson Rockefeller," hosted by Jim Leher of National Public Affairs Center for Television (NPACT). Paul Duke(NPACT) and Richard Reeves from New York Magazine report on Rockefeller and his role as governor. Carolyn Lewis reports on Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller's 1972 lobbying for a Grumman aircraft defense contract for New York. Leher provides a synposis of what topics were covered during Day Two of Senate questioning.
    Tape continues with Day Two of Senate Hearings: Senator Howard Cannon begins by reading a prepared statement regarding the three major national television network's decision not to "live" broadcast the hearings. Nelson Rockefeller begins by supplementing his answers to certain questions from the previous day, particulary about capital gains and his income taxes, the worth of Rockefeller Center, and the ACLU lawsuit.
    Senator Robert Byrd questions Rockefeller about his wealth and influence, stating he disregards these attributes as being "a myth." Rockefeller responds, and speaks to Byrd's next question regarding the recent energy crisis and the role oil companies played.
    Senator Robert Griffin asks about the Attica prison riots. Rockefeller speaks at length about this event and prison reform.
    Senator James Allen questions why men of great wealth in politics tend to take a liberal stance. Rockefeller discusses his political philosophies, particularly in regard to American incomes and the distribution of wealth. He discusses his accomplishments with increased enrollment in State University of New York schools (SUNY), and concludes by talking about his capacity to balance business interest and national interest.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day Two (Tape 8), 1974; Sound, Color, 57 minutes; U-matic (Box 5, Tape AV 12014)
    Senator Mark Hatfield asks about potential conflict of interest and Nelson Rockefeller states that there cannot be conflict of interest if a person takes his/her oath of office seriously. Rockefeller answers questions regarding the current housing crisis and questions regarding mass transit, in particular the idea of using Highway Trust funds for mass transit construction. Rockefeller speaks about how to help restore the American people's confidence in their political system, and the important role in using the medium of television to communicate.
    Senator Harrison Williams begins questioning. Rockefeller answers questions regarding mass transportation, the current depression in the construction industry, and the needs of people and families affected by mental disabilities.
    Senator Howard Cannon clarifies facts about the Grumman aircraft contract and Rockefeller speaks more about that deal. Cannon continues his questioning, asking about pardons. Rockefeller discusses his views about whether Nixon should be prosecuted, reflects on his commuting Lyman Judson Morehouse's conviction in 1960s, and provides more answers in regard to the Attica prisoners demands for amnesty.
    Tape ends with Senate Rules Committee breaking for midday reccess.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day Two (Tape 9), 1974; Sound, Color, 63 minutes; U-matic (Box 6, Tape AV 12015)
    Tape begins post-midday recess.
    Senator Mark Hatfield asks about Rockefeller's relationship with his income. Rockefeller responds by discussing his upbringing as a boy, learning the value of money, receiving an allowance and creating an annual budget. He speaks about his current money-related procedures.
    Nelson Rockefeller answers Senator Claiborne Pell's questions about where Rockefeller plans to place his personal and official papers, the plans for a 1976 Bicentennial celebration, public finacing of campaigns for federal office, budget reductions, and the United State's relationship with Cuba.
    Senator James Allen asks about the minimum tax for the wealthy.
    Rockefeller speaks at length about forced school busing of students to acheive racial balance and the desegregation of public schools. Senator Allen asks Rockefeller to discuss his past comments regarding voluntary prayer in public schools. Rockefeller asks to be able to review his past comments and would answer this question at a later time.
    Senator Hugh Scott reads for the record a letter he has drafted recommending further funding to the Public Broadcasting System (PBS) and commended PBS for their coverage of these hearings.
    Senator Marlow Cook relates additional details regarding the Gumman aircraft deal. Rockefeller answers questions about limiting campaign financing, time limit on campaigning, and financial contributions by family members.
    Rockefeller discusses his views on gun control and his record on gun control as governor of New York. He speaks about his various residencies and the needed security.
    Cook asks about the role Rockefeller envisions for himself in regard to international affairs and his relationship with Secretary of State Henry Kissinger.
    Senator Byrd questions Rockefeller regarding his views on continuing the process of impeachment to reveal all the facts pertaining to Watergate. Byrd voices his concern that the agreement Nixon entered into.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day Two (Tape 10), 1974 September 24; Sound, Color, 47 minutes; U-matic (Box 6, Tape AV 12016)
    Day Two continues.
    Nelson A. Rockefeller says he is not wanting to make a quick statement regarding the Watergate agreement given that he does not have all the information.
    Sen. Harrison Williams asks about the Commission on Critical Choices for Americans (CCCA). Rockefeller explains in depth the CCCA's origins, its members, and the work of this group. He also discusses property jointly owned with his family.
    Sen. Howard Cannon questions Rockefeller about how he could ensure his staff would meet the highest standards of personal conduct. Cannon asks about the privacy of citizens. Rockefeller speaks about his wiretapping program in New York, which he put into place to reduce crime and police corruption.
    Rockefeller provides a list of his stock holdings for the record, and supplies further details about his established blind trust.
    End of Day Two.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day Three (Tape 11), 1974 September 25; Sound, Color, 62 minutes; U-matic (Box 6, Tape AV 12017)
    Tape begins with special PBS-TV report: "Washington: Senate Hearings on Nelson Rockefeller," hosted by Paul Duke of National Public Affairs Center for Television (NPACT). Richard Reeves from New York Magazine and Carl Leubsdorf of the Associated Press report on Rockefeller's testimony given during Day Three. Duke provides a synposis of key topics that were covered during Day Three of Senate questioning.
    Tape continues with Day Three of Senate Hearings: Nelson A. Rockefeller begins by suppying more details about his trusts and their relationship to his children.
    Sen. Robert Griffin begins questions about Latin America. Rockefeller speaks at length about his and his family's interests and long history in Latin America.
    Sen. Claiborne Pell asks about revisions to Social Security and Rockefeller's thoughts about the Bilateral Military Assistance Program. He also asks about "qualitative" versus "quantitative" growth.
    Senator Robert Byrd questions Rockefeller about the overwhelming problems in respect to inflation, unemployment, and economic stagnation. Rockefeller discusses at length about the need to increase productivity at home and abroad in food, energy, and raw material. Also, he speaks about the need to create incentives for capital formation.
    Rockefeller answers Senator Marlow Cook's question regarding why he accepted the Vice President nomination. Cook follows up with a line of economic questions and the federal government's relationship with the private sector.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day Three (Tape 12), 1975 September 25; Sound, Color, 62 minutes; U-matic (Box 6, Tape AV 12018)
    Day Three of hearings continue.
    Nelson A. Rockefeller continues his statement regarding declassifying and making available scientific information.
    Sen. Hugh Scott asks about state lottery programs. Rockefeller details the New York State lottery programs and the federal government's role. Sen. Marlow Cook speaks about the problem's with off-track betting.
    Sen. James Allen asks about the National Debt. Rockefeller discusses his approach to balancing the budget by cutting and holding down expenses. He also speaks about the United State's relationship with Russia and current trade deal with the Soviet Union. Sen. Allen requests Rockefeller's opinions of Henry Kissinger.
    Rockefeller reports he did not furnish funds for the Watergate cover up, and reveals he did not contribute money to Spiro Agnew after the vice president's resignation. Rockefeller's personal financial details are further discussed.
    Rockefeller discusses at length about tax-exempt foundations and his family's relationship with foundations and philanthropy.
    Sen. Marlow Cook makes a statement on recent off-shore oil and gas leases.
    Sen. James Allen asks for Rockefeller's attitude toward capital punishment. Rockefeller discusses his history with this penalty.
    Rockefeller discusses his past remarks relating to a constitutional amendment for prayer in public school.
    Sen. Howard Cannon asks Rockefeller to clarify his past remarks about Nixon's transparency during Watergate, of the Watergate investigation committee, and past allegations made against Rockefeller while he was governor, including his controversy with Ross Perot.
    Rockefeller speaks about his Albany South Mall project.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day Three (Tape 13), 1974 September 25; Sound, Color, 62 minutes; U-matic (Box 6, Tape AV 12019)
    Nelson Rockefeller continues discussing his Albany South Mall project.
    Sen. Hugh Cannon asks about why there were conflicting reports about the hostages' deaths during the Attica prison riots. Rockefeller explains.
    Sen. Robert Byrd asks about wage negotiations.
    Rockefeller and Sen. Byrd speak at great length about executive privilege.
    Sen. Robert Griffin asks which house Rockefeller plans to live in if becoming Vice President; Sen. Cannon asks whether Rockefeller recently channelled any funds to savings and loans institutions. Rockefeller tells his ideas for bringing down the cost of gas and oil, and about if he received any valuable gifts from heads of state.
    Rockefeller states that he does not think there is anything in his past that will cause Americans further disillusionment or disappointment in the U.S. government.
    Rockefeller clarifies comments made by himself the previous day regarding the mentally handicapped, and details his history with this community.
    Senators break for midday recess.
    Tape concludes with closing remarks from PBS-TV report: "Washington: Senate Hearings on Nelson Rockefeller," hosted by Paul Duke of National Public Affairs Center for Television (NPACT). Also featured: Richard Reeves from New York Magazine and Carl Leubsdorf of the Associated Press report. (Tape ends. Incomplete. This PBS reporting can be seen complete at start of tape AV 12020)
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Day Three (Tape 14), 1974 September 25; Sound, Color, 54 minutes; U-matic (Box 6, Tape AV 12020)
    Tape begins with remarks from PBS-TV report: "Washington: Senate Hearings on Nelson Rockefeller," hosted by Paul Duke of National Public Affairs Center for Television (NPACT). Duke summarizes events from the first part of Day Three of hearings. Also featured: Richard Reeves from New York Magazine and Carl Leubsdorf of the Associated Press report. Reporters discuss their views on Rockefeller's performance.
    NPACT program ends at 13:30.
    Beginning at 14:45: "The Captioned ABC Evening News" from September 25, 1975. This is a rebroadcast prepared for the hearing impaired. Newscasters report on the news of the day.
    Beginning at 47:30: Selection of clips from Senate Rules Committee Hearings of various senators speaking about the U.S. television networks' decision to not broadcast the hearings in their entirely.
    Tape ends at 54 minutes.
  - Senate Rules Committee: Nelson A. Rockefeller's Vice Presidential Hearings - Reconvening - Day Four (Tape 15), 1974 November 13; U-matic; Sound, Color, 62 minutes (Box 6, Tape AV 12021)
    After completing testimony in September 1974, Nelson A. Rockefeller returns to the Senate Rules Committee to answer questions regarding gifts and loans to public servants and the financing of a book critical of an election opponent.
    Senator Howard Cannon makes short opening statements, recapiltulating previous history of the hearings and expressing four new areas of concern: 1. Nelson Rockefeller's involvment in Victor J. Lasky's biography "Arthur J. Goldberg: The Old and The New" 2. Nelson Rockefeller's and other Rockefeller family members' political campaign contributions 3. Tax questions for the years 1969-1974 4. Nelson Rockefeller's loans and/or gifts made to friends, aides, political associates, and others.
    Senator Hugh Scott makes statement about the lack of television coverage of the earlier hearings, but that these reconvened hearings are being televised.
    Nelson Rockefeller begins his opening statements. Happy Rockefeller appears behind him. Key point, he discusses the Rockefeller history of sharing and no gifts, loans, or forgivement of a loan were politically motivated. He details his relationship with and loans to Dr. William J. Ronan, architecht of the Metropolitan Transit Authority (MTA).
    Nelson Rockefeller admits he made a mistake in terms of the Goldberg book, and discusses that book's history and Laurance Rockefeller's involvement.
    Rockefeller begins to discuss his audits and returns from the previous seven years. He states the past five years had not been audited.